Edward Millman Papers
Edward Millman Papers
1921-1969
Millman, Edward, 1907-1964.
3.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American Jewish muralist, painter, and educator. Born in Chicago.
Correspondence, family, personal, and business (1921-1969); original artwork and reproductions, including photographs of the Federal Art Project murals in Illinois and St. Louis; research material, sketches, photographs of paintings of steel-works which Millman executed for the Gimbel Pennsylvania Art Collection; as well as sketchbooks, sketches, and photographs relating to Millman's combat paintings for the U.S. Navy; writings, which encompass essays and notes on art as well as combat journal entries; and memorabilia, including financial material, photographs of Millman, clippings (1933-1964), and exhibition catalogs and announcements (1936-1953). Correspondents include Aaron Bohrod, Ilya Bolotowsky, Ralston Crawford, Richard A. Florsheim, Norbert Heermann, Kenneth Hudson, Amy Freeman Lee, Edmund Lewandowski, Fletcher Martin, Reginald Neal, William C. Palmer, Stuart R. Purser, George Rickey, Mitchell Siporin, David Smith, Prentiss Taylor, and Ralph L. Wickiser.
149507
Biographical History
Edward Millman was born in Chicago on January 1st, 1907 and died in Woodstock, NY on February 11, 1964. He was a painter, muralist, educator and lecturer. He studied at the Chicago Art School under Leon Knoll during the years 1923-1928, and then later was taught privately in Mexico City by Diego Rivera, where he studied fresco painting, between the years 1934-1935. He won the Guggenheim Foundation Fellowship in 1945 and the Ohio University First Prize in 1952. He taught at a number of major universities throughout the United States, starting with the Florida Gulf Coast Art Center, Inc. in 1951 and working finally at Renssalaer Polytechnic Institute from 1956 until his death.
Source: Cummings, Paul. Dictionary of Contemporary American Artists, 3rd ed. St. Martin's Press, New York, 1977.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1921 to 1969, the Edward Millman Papers comprises biographical material, family, personal and business correspondence, artwork, writings, and memorabilia of the Chicago-born artist (1907-1964). In addition to documenting Millman's role as mural painter for the Federal Art Project, combat artist for the United States Navy during World War II, and artist-in-residence at numerous academic institutions, the collection illuminates the artistic versatility of the Jewish-American muralist, painter, and educator.
Arranged alphabetically, the Correspondence-subject files (Boxes 1-3) consists of incoming and outgoing letters, legal contracts, museum receipts and acceptances, photographs, recommendations, and sales records. A number of letters are addressed to Millman's wife, Norma, including sympathy cards an his passing. Among Millman's correspondents are fellow artists (Charles Baskerville, Aaron Bohrod, Ilya Bolotowsky, Ralston Crawford, Bruce Currie, David Durst, Philip Clarkson Elliott, Richard A. Florsheim, B. Sturtevant Gardner, John Anthony Hartell, Norbert Leo Heermann, Kenneth Eugene Hudson, Dwight Kirsch, Amy Freeman Lee, Beatrice S. Levy, Edmund D. Lewandowski, Margaret Lowengrund, Fletcher Martin, Reginald H. Neal, John O'Neil, William C. Palmer, Stuart R. Purser, Florine Rensie, George Warren Rickey, Mitchell Siporin, David Smith, Prentiss Taylor, Howard Thomas, Dorothy Varian, Ralph Lewanda Wickiser, Denny Winters); as well as art galleries and museums (Alan Gallery, Albany Institute of History and Art, Albright Art Gallery, Art Institute of Chicago, Associated American Artists Galleries, Butler Institute of American Art, Downtown Gallery, Florida Gulf Coast Art Center, Herron Museum of Art, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute, Museum of Modern Art, Nordness Gallery, Rudolph Galleries). Other correspondence relates to Millman's relationship with clients (Chrysler Corporation, Contemporary Design, Inc., Fortune, Foster Grant Co., Inc., Gimbel Pennsylvania Art Collection, Glencoe, Illinois, United States Navy, United States Treasury Department); and educational institutions (Brandeis University, Colgate University, Cornell University, Eastern Illinois State College, Florida State University, Indiana University, Layton School of Art, Louisiana State University, Ohio University, Purdue University, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Southern Illinois University, Southwestern Louisiana Institute, and Universities of Arkansas, Buffalo, Chattanooga, Florida, Georgia, Kansas City, Wisconsin, and Wyoming).
Artwork (Boxes 4-6) encompasses material pertaining to Federal Art Project murals, Gimbel Pennsylvania Art Collection, restaurant murals, United States Navy combat paintings, and miscellaneous subjects. Photographs and negatives of murals produced for the Federal Art Project include those for buildings in Illinois (Chicago's City Hall and Lucy Flower Technical High School, Decatur Post Office, and Moline Post Office), as well as the St. Louis Post Office in Missouri. Millman's contribution to the Gimbel Pennsylvania Art Collection is recorded by research material (photographs of steel mills), original sketches, and photographs of finished paintings. Various stages of completion of restaurant murals painted by Millman are documented by photographs and negatives. United States Navy combat art is represented by one sketchbook, original sketches, and photographs of finished paintings arranged in numerical sequence. Miscellaneous artwork is comprised of original Florida wash drawings, 10 lithographic proofs, 12 sketchbook pages, 2 sketchbooks, and pencil and ink sketches. Photographs of miscellaneous paintings are arranged by title when available.
Titled and untitled Statements on art constitute Writings (Box 6). Titled pieces include course descriptions, essays, and exhibition press releases. Artwork descriptions, combat Journal entries, and miscellaneous drafts and fragments are among untitled works.
Memorabilia (Boxes 6-7) comprises address lists, financial material, a lecture tour itinerary, lists of artwork (partially annotated with prices), miscellaneous research references, photographs, printed material, unidentified artwork and reproductions, and an essay by Arthur Siegel. European trip receipts, income tax documentation, and miscellaneous receipts constitute financial material. Photographs include those of Millman, as well as teaching-related subjects and a number of unidentified artist portraits. Printed material contains newspaper clippings about Millman (1933-1964) and several exhibition catalogs and announcements (1936-1953).
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence - subject files is organized alphabetically by name of the institution or person. Artwork is divided into five sections: the Federal Art Project, the Gimbel Pennsylvania Art Collection, restaurant murals, navy sketches, and miscellaneous. Artwork is separated into originals and photographs of originals, and is ordered by type (sketches, drawings, lithographs) or title, where applicable. Writings includes a section on statements on art and miscellaneous. Statements on art is divided into titled and untitled. Writings is organized alphabetically by the name of the artwork being described (when available) or by a descriptive title in the case of untitled works. Memorabilia is also organized alphabetically by type of material.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Bohrod, Aaron.; Bolotowsky, Ilya, 1907-1981.; Crawford, Ralston, 1906-1978.; Florsheim, Richard A., 1916-1979.; Heermann, Norbert.; Hudson, Kenneth Eugene.; Lee, Amy Freeman.; Lewandowski, Edmund.; Martin, Fletcher, 1904-1979.; Millman, Edward, 1907-1964.; Neal, Reginald, 1909-; Palmer, William C., 1906-1987.; Purser, Stuart R., 1907-1986.; Rickey, George.; Siporin, Mitchell, 1910-1976.; Smith, David, 1906-1965.; Taylor, Prentiss, 1907-1991.; Wickiser, Ralph L. (Ralph Lewanda), 1910-1998.; Federal Art Project.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Art and state -- United States.; Jewish artists -- United States.; Federal aid to the arts -- United States.; Jews, American.; Mural painting and decoration -- United States -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Steel-works in art.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Art and the war.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Essays.; Exhibition catalogs.; Photographs.; Sketchbooks.; Sketches.; Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Norma Millman, 1977.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Family correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, 1944-1968; undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Alan Gallery (New York), 1952-1957; undated (Box 1)
  - Albany Institute of History and Art, 1954-1964; undated (Box 1)
  - Albright Art Gallery (Buffalo, NY), 1955; 1956 (Box 1)
  - Albright Art School (Buffalo, NY), See University of Buffalo.
  - American Federation of Arts, 1948; 1955 (Box 1)
  - Art Association of Indianapolis, See Herron Museum of Art.
  - Art Institute of Chicago, 1921-1962; undated (Box 1)
  - Art Students League of New York, 1948-1964 (Box 1)
  - Artists Equity Association, 1947; 1951 (Box 1)
  - Associated American Artists Galleries (New York), 1944-1952; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Association of American Colleges, 1952-1954; undated (Box 1)
  - Baird, Bill, 1962; undated (Box 1)
  - Baskerville, Charles, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Bocour Artist Colors, Inc. (New York), 1951-1959 (Box 1)
  - Bohrod, Aaron, 1964; undated (Box 1)
  - Bolotowsky, Ilya, See University of Wyoming.
  - Bookbinder, Jack, See Philadelphia Board of Public Education.
  - Brandeis University, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - Butler Institute of American Art (Youngstown, OH), 1967 (Box 1)
  - Cahill, Holger, 1942 (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Institute, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Chrysler Corporation, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Clear, Charles Val, see Florida Gulf Coast Art Center.
  - Coiner, Charles Toucey, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Cole, Sylvan, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Colgate University, 1956 (Box 1)
  - College Art Association of America, 1954 (Box 1)
  - The Contemporaries (New York), See Lowengrund, Margaret.
  - Contemporary Design, Inc. (New York), 1949 (Box 1)
  - Cornell University, 1954-1956 (Box 1)
  - Crawford, Ralston, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Currie, Bruce, 1956; 1958,; undated (Box 1)
  - Defenbacher, Daniel S., 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - Downtown Gallery (New York), 1943; 1956,; 1958 (Box 1)
  - Durst, David, See University of Arkansas.
  - Eastern Illinois State College, 1948-1949 (Box 1)
  - Elliott, Philip Clarkson, See University of Buffalo.
  - Federal Art Project, See United States Treasury Department; Artwork: Federal Art Project; Writings: Statements on art: Untitled: Artwork descriptions: Illinois murals.
  - Florida Gulf Coast Art Center, 1950; 1952 (Box 1)
  - Florida State University, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - Florsheim, Richard A. and Helen, 1964; 1969,; undated (Box 1)
  - Fortress, Karl, undated (Box 1)
  - Fortune, 1947-1955 (Box 1)
    See also Writings: Statements on art: Untitled: Artwork descriptions: Combat paintings.
  - Foster Grant Co., Inc. (Leominster, MA), 1955 (Box 1)
  - Freilich, Michael Leon, undated (Box 1)
  - Fuller, R. Buckminster, 1960; 1963,; undated (Box 1)
  - Gardner, B. Sturtevant, undated (Box 2)
  - Genders, Richard Atherstone, undated (Box 2)
  - Gimbel Brothers (Pittsburgh), 1946-1948 (Box 2)
  - Gimbel Pennsylvania Art Collection, See Gimbel Brothers; Artwork: Gimbel Pennsylvania Art Collection.
  - Glencoe, Illinois, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Goldberg, Bertrand, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Gonzalez. Xavier, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Grafly, Dorothy, 1947 (Box 2)
  - Halpert, Edith Gregor, 1964 (Box 2)
    See also Downtown Gallery.
  - Hartell, John Anthony, See Cornell University.
  - Heermann, Norbert Leo, undated (Box 2)
  - Heller, Deltah Co., Inc (New York), 1948 (Box 2)
  - Herron Museum of Art (Indianapolis), 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - Hope, Henry Radford, See Indiana University.
  - Hudson, Kenneth Eugene, 1953-1955 (Box 2)
  - Indiana University, 1948-1964; undated (Box 2)
  - Janis, Sidney, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Kerechuk, Florence, 1953; 1955 (Box 2)
  - Kirsch, Dwight, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Komroff, Manuel, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Layton School of Art (Milwaukee), 1954-1956; undated (Box 2)
  - Lee, Amy Freeman, 1953; 1954 (Box 2)
  - Levine, Jack, 1953; undated (Box 2)
  - Levy, Beatrice S., 1949 (Box 2)
  - Lewandowski, Edmund D., See Florida State University; Layton School of Art.
  - Louisiana State University, 1946-1952; undated (Box 2)
  - Lowengrund, Margaret, 1952 (Box 2)
  - MacDonald, John D., 1961 (Box 2)
  - Martin, Fletcher, 1946; 1964,; undated (Box 2)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York), 1950 (Box 2)
  - Miller, Dorothy Canning, See Museum of Modern Art.
  - Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute (Utica, NY), 1954-1964; undated (Box 2)
  - Museum of Modern Art (New York), 1944; 1954,; undated (Box 2)
  - Mydans, Carl, 1945 (Box 2)
  - Neal, Reginald H., 1954-1956 (Box 2)
  - Nordness, Lee, See Nordness Gallery.
  - Nordness Gallery (New York), 1959-1964 (Box 2)
  - Ohio University, 1952 (Box 2)
  - O'Neil, John, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Palmer, William C., See Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute.
  - Peat, Wilbur David, See Herron Museum of Art.
  - Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Pepsi-Cola's Annual Art Competition, 1948-1949 (Box 2)
  - Philadelphia Board of Public Education, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Pollack, Peter, 1963; undated (Box 2)
    See also Art Institute of Chicago.
  - Purdue University, 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - Purser, Stuart R., See University of Chattanooga; University of Florida.
  - Radulovic, Savo, undated (Box 2)
  - Rensie, Florine, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, 1959-1964 (Box 2)
  - Rich, Daniel Catton, See Art Institute of Chicago.
  - Rickey, George Warren, 1952-1964; undated (Box 2)
  - Roberson Memorial Center (Binghamton, NY), 1956 (Box 2)
  - Rudolph Galleries (Woodstock, NY), 1949; 1954 (Box 2)
  - Samuel, Ray, 1945-1949 (Box 2)
  - Sepeshy, Zolton L., 1956 (Box 2)
  - Siporin, Mitchell, 1943 (Box 2)
    See also Brandeis University; Artwork: Federal Art Project: Missouri.
  - Smith, David and Jean Freas, 1953-1969; undated (Box 2)
  - Southern Illinois University, 1949; 1960,; undated (Box 2)
  - Southwestern Louisiana Institute, 1947 (Box 2)
  - Taylor, Prentiss, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Texas Watercolor Society, 1952-1953 (Box 2)
  - Thomas, Howard, See University of Georgia.
  - United States Navy, 1942-1960; undated; 3 folders (Box 2)
    See also Artwork: United States Navy; Writings: Statements on art: Untitled: Artwork descriptions: Combat paintings; Writings: Statements on art: Untitled: Journal entries (combat).
  - United States Treasury Department, 1935-1945 (Box 2)
    See also Artwork: Federal Art Project; Writings: Statements on art: untitled: Artwork descriptions: Illinois murals.
  - University of Arkansas, 1948-1954; undated (Box 3)
  - University of Buffalo, 1954-1964; undated (Box 3)
  - University of Chattanooga, 1949 (Box 3)
  - University of Florida, 1948-1954 (Box 3)
  - University of Georgia, 1954 (Box 3)
  - University of Kansas City, 1947-1949 (Box 3)
  - University of Wisconsin, 1942; 1953,; 1955 (Box 3)
  - University of Wyoming, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Varian, Dorothy, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Walker, Hudson D., undated (Box 3)
    See also Artists Equity Association.
  - Watson, Forbes, 1948 (Box 3)
    See also United States Treasury Department.
  - Wickiser, Ralph Lewanda, See Louisiana State University.
  - Winters, Denny, undated (Box 3)
  - Wolfert, Helen X. Herschdorfer, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Woodstock Artists Association, 1950; 1953 (Box 3)
  - Woodstock Foundation, 1953-1954 (Box 3)
  - A-Z, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Unidentified (Box 3)
- Artwork
  - Federal Art Project
    See also Correspondence - subject files: United States Treasury Department.
    - Photographs, negatives
      - Illinois
        - General (Box 4)
        - Chicago, City Hall Bureau of Water (Box 4)
        - Chicago, Lucy Flower Technical High School (Box 4)
        - Decatur Post Office (Box 4)
          See also Writings: Statements on art: Untitled: Artwork descriptions.
        - Moline Post Office (Box 4)
      - Missouri
        - St. Louis Post Office (Box 4)
  - Gimbel Pennsylvania Art Collection
    - Research material, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Original sketches (Box 4)
    - Photographs, by title (Box 4)
      See also Correspondence: Subject files: Gimbel Brothers
  - Restaurant murals
    - Photographs, negatives (Box 5)
  - United States Navy
    - Combat sketchbook (Box 5)
    - Original combat sketches (Box 5)
    - Photographs of combat paintings, by number (Box 5)
      See also Correspondence - subject files: United States Navy; Writings: Statements on art: Untitled: Artwork descriptions: Combat paintings; Writings: Statements on art: Untitled: Journal entries (combat).
  - Miscellaneous
    - Original
      - Florida wash drawings (Box 5)
        See also Writings: Statements on art: Untitled: Artwork descriptions: Southern states paintings.
      - Lithographic proofs, 10 items (Box 5)
      - Sketchbook pages, watercolor/crayon wash drawings; 12 items (Box 5)
      - Sketchbooks, 2 books in 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Sketches - pencil ink (Box 5)
    - Photographs, negatives
      - By title (Box 5)
      - Untitled, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Writings
  - Statements on art
    - Titled
      - "Architecture 312", course description (Box 6)
      - "The Contemporary Artists Image", essay (Box 6)
      - "The Grammar of Art", exhibition description (Box 6)
      - "A Philippine Diary", exhibition press release, painting descriptions (Box 6)
      - "Symbolism in Wall Painting", essay (Box 6)
      - "The Use of the Object in Painting", essay (Box 6)
    - Untitled
      - Artwork descriptions
        - Combat paintings (Box 6)
          See also Correspondence - subject files: Fortune; Correspondence - subject files: United States Navy; Artwork: United States Navy.
        - Illinois murals, Decatur Post Office (Box 6)
          See also Correspondence - subject files: United States Treasury Department; Artwork: Federal Art Project.
        - Southern states paintings (Box 6)
          See also Artwork: Miscellaneous: Original: Florida wash drawings.
      - Journal entries (combat), 1944 (Box 6)
        See also Correspondence - subject files: United States Navy; Artwork: United States Navy.
      - Miscellaneous
        - Holograph, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Typescript (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Memorabilia
  - Address lists (Box 6)
  - Financial
    - European trip receipts and information, 1956-1957 (Box 6)
    - Income tax documentation, 1946-1950 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous receipts, 1948-1967 (Box 6)
  - Lecture tour, itinerary, questions, and comments (Box 6)
  - Lists of artwork, some with prices (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous research references (Box 6)
  - Photographs
    - Millman, Edward, undated (Box 7)
    - Millman, Edward with others, undated (Box 7)
    - Teaching-related, undated (Box 7)
    - Unidentified artists, undated (Box 7)
  - Printed material
    - Clippings, 1933-1964; undated (Box 7)
    - Exhibition catalogs, announcements, 1936-1953; undated (Box 7)
  - Unidentified artwork and reproductions (Box 7)
  - Writings by others
    - Siegel, Arthur, typescript essay (Box 7)